<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2328 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5340 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5340.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1195 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1195.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5286 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5286.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7490 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7490.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5331 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5331.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8102 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8102.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-hegde-spring-node-protection-for-sr-te-paths-03" ipr="trust200902">
<front>
  <title abbrev="Node Protection for SR-TE Paths">Node Protection for SR-TE Paths</title>

  <author initials="S." surname="Hegde" fullname="Shraddha Hegde">
    <organization>Juniper Networks Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Exora Business Park</street>
        <city>Bangalore</city>
        <region>KA</region>
        <code>560103</code>
        <country>India</country>
      </postal>
      <email>shraddha@juniper.net</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  
  <author initials="C." surname="Bowers" fullname="Chris Bowers">
    <organization>Juniper Networks Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city></city>
        <region></region>
        <code></code>
        <country></country>
      </postal>
      <email>cbowers@juniper.net</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="S." surname="Litkowski" fullname="Stephane Litkowski">
    <organization>Orange</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city></city>
        <region></region>
        <code></code>
        <country></country>
      </postal>
      <email>stephane.litkowski@orange.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  
  <author initials="X." surname="Xu" fullname="Xiaohu Xu">
    <organization>Alibaba Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <region></region>
        <code></code>
        <country>China</country>
      </postal>
      <email>xiaohu.xxh@alibaba-inc.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
	
  <author initials="F." surname="Xu" fullname="Feng Xu">
    <organization>Tencent</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city></city>
        <region></region>
        <code></code>
        <country>China</country>
      </postal>
      <email>oliverxu@tencent.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  
  <date year="2018"/>
  <area>Routing</area>
  <workgroup>Routing area</workgroup>
  <keyword>PLR</keyword>
  <keyword>IGP</keyword>
  <keyword>OSPF</keyword>
  <keyword>IS-IS</keyword>
  <keyword>SPRING</keyword>
  <abstract>
 <t>Segment routing supports the creation of explicit paths using 
adjacency-sids, node-sids, and binding-sids. It is important to provide 
fast reroute (FRR) mechanisms to respond to failures of links and nodes 
in the Segment-Routed Traffic-Engineered(SR-TE) path. A point of local 
repair (PLR) can provide FRR protection against the failure of a link in 
an SR-TE path by examining only the first (top) label in the SR label 
stack. In order to protect against the failure of a node, a PLR may need 
to examine the second label in the stack as well in order to determine 
SR-TE path beyond the failed node. This document specifies how a PLR can 
use the first and second label in the label stack describing an SR-TE 
path to provide protection against node failures. </t> 

  </abstract>

  <note title="Requirements Language">
    <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
    target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
  </note>

</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction" anchor='intro'>
<t> It is possible for a routing device to completely go out of 
service abruptly due to power failure, hardware failure or software 
crashes. Node protection is an important property of the Fast Reroute 
mechanism. It provides protection against a node failure by rerouting 
traffic around the failed node. For example, the mechanisms described in 
Loop Free Alternates (<xref target="RFC5286"/>),  
Remote Loop Free Alternates (<xref target="RFC8102"/>), and 
<xref target ='I-D.bashandy-rtgwg-segment-routing-ti-lfa'/> can be
used to provide node protection to ensure minimal traffic loss after 
a node failure.  </t> 

<t><xref target="Problems_with_SR_TE"/> describes problems with SR-TE 
paths and the need for a specialized mechanism to provide node protection 
for SR-TE paths. <xref target="detailed-soln"/> describes the 
solution applied to paths built using adjacency-sids and node-sids. 
 </t> 

</section>

  <section anchor='Problems_with_SR_TE' title='Node Failures Along SR-TE Paths'>

<t>The topology shown in <xref target="example_topology"/>. illustrates a 
example network topology with SPRING enabled on each node.</t> 
  
    <figure anchor="example_topology" title="Example topology. The segment
 index for each node is shown in the diagram. All nodes have SRGB = [1000-2000],
 except for R8 which has SRGB = [3000-4000].  A label stack that
 represents the path R1->R7->R8->R4->R5 is shown as well.">
      <artwork>
   Node          Node          Node          Node          Node
   sid:1         sid:2         sid:3         sid:4         sid:5  
   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+
   | R1 |--------| R2 |--------| R3 |--------| R4 |--------| R5 |
   +----+        +----+        +----+        +----+        +----+
       \                           \          /
        \ 10                        \ 100    / 60
         \                           \      /
          \   +----+                  +----+   
           +--| R7 |------------------| R8 |
              +----+    30            +----+
             / Node                   Node             Label stack:
            /  sid:7                  sid:8            +------------+
      +----+                          SRGB:            |  1008 (top)|
      | R6 |                          3000-4000        +------------+
      +----+                                           |  3005      |
      Node                                             +------------+
      sid:6
      </artwork>
    </figure>

<section title='Node protection for node-sid explicit paths'>

<t>Consider an explicit path in the topology in <xref 
target="example_topology"/> from R1->R5 via R1->R7->R8->R4->R5. This 
path can be built using the shortest paths from R1-to-R8 and R8-to-R5. 
The label stack to instantiate this path contains two node-sids 1008 and 
3005. The 1008 label will take the packet from R1 to R8 via R7 and get 
popped. The next label in the stack 3005 will take the packet from R8 to 
the destination R5 via R4. If the node R8 goes down, it is not possible 
for R7 to perform FRR without examining the second label in the incoming 
label stack (3005).</t> 

<t>Note that in the absence of a failure, R7 does not need to understand 
the meaning of the second label (3005) in order to perform normal 
forwarding. However, in order to support node protection, R7 will need 
to understand the meaning of label 3005 in order to determine where the 
packet is headed after R8. </t> 

</section>

 <section anchor='Anycast_prefixes' title='Node-Protection for Anycast-SIDs'>

<t>A prefix segment advertised as a node SID may only be advertised by one node in 
the network.  Instead, an anycast prefix segment may be advertised by more than one node.
In some situations, one can use anycast SIDs to construct SR-TE paths that are 
protected against node failure, without the need for the mechanism described 
in this document.  
</t> 

<figure anchor="anycast_example" title="Topology illustrating use of 
anycast-sids to protect against node failures.
All nodes have SRGB = [1000-2000].">
      <artwork> 
   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+
   | R1 |--------| R2 |--------| R3 |--------| R4 |--------| R5 |
   +----+        +----+        +----+        +----+        +----+
       \                           \          / |
        \ 10                        \100   60/  |  
         \                           \      /   | 
          \   +----+    30            +----+    |
           +--| R7 |------------------| R8 |    | 
              +----+                  +----+    |
             /    \                  Anycast    +               
            /      \                 sid:100   /                  
      +----+        \                         /             
      | R6 |         \    40          +----+ /60                            
      +----+          +---------------| R9 |+          Label stack:  
                                      +----+           +------------+
                                     Anycast           |  1100 (top)|
                                     sid:100           +------------+
                                                       |  1005      |
                                                       +------------+
      </artwork>
    </figure>

<t>
An example of this is shown in <xref target="anycast_example"/>.
In this example, R8 and R9 advertise an anycast SID of 100. 
The label stack in this example = [1100, 1005];.
The top label (1100) corresponds to the anycast SID advertised by 
both R8 and R9.   In the absence of a failure, 
the packet sent by R1 with this label stack will follow the path
from R1->R5 along R1->R7->R8->R4->R5.
</t> 

<t> If R7 is performing a per-prefix LFA calculation <xref target ="RFC5286"/>,
then R7 will install a backup next-hop to R9 for this anycast SID,
protecting against the failure of the primary next-hop to R8.
This backup path does not pass through R8, so it is would not
be affected by a complete failure of node R8. As illustrated 
by this example, for some topologies node-protecting SR-TE paths
can constructed through the use of anycast SIDs, as opposed 
to the mechanism described in this document.
</t> 

</section>


    
<section title='Node-protection for adj-sid explicit paths'>
    
<figure anchor="Explicit_path_adj_sid" title="Explicit path using an adjacency sid.
All nodes have SRGB = [1000-2000], except for R8 which has SRGB = [3000-4000].">
<artwork>
                               Adj-sid:
                               R3-R8:9044

   Node          Node          Node          Node          Node
   sid:1         sid:2         sid:3         sid:4         sid:5  
   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+   10   +----+
   | R1 |--------| R2 |--------| R3 |--------| R4 |--------| R5 |
   +----+        +----+        +----+        +----+        +----+
       \                           \          /              |   
        \ 10                        \ 100    / 60            | 10
         \                           \      /                |   
          \   +----+                  +----+               +----+
           +--| R7 |------------------| R8 |---------------| R9 |
              +----+    30            +----+      10       +----+
             / Node                   Node                 Node       
            /  sid:7                  sid:8                sid:9     
      +----+                          SRGB:                           
      | R6 |                          3000-4000        Label stack:  
      +----+                                           +------------+
      Node                            Adj-sids:        |  1003 (top)|
      sid:6                           R8-R4:9054       +------------+
                                                       |  9044      |
                                                       +------------+ 
                                                       |  9054      | 
                                                       +------------+ 
                                                       |  1005      |          	
                                                       +------------+  																			
      </artwork>
    </figure>
 <t>Consider an explicit path from R1->R5 via R1->R2->R3->R8->R4->R5. 
This path can be built using a combination of node sids and adjacency sids,
as shown in <xref target='Explicit_path_adj_sid'/>. The diagram shows 
the label stack needed to instantiate this path, as well as 
several adjacency sids advertised by nodes involved in this path.
When a packet leaving R1 with this label stack  
reaches R3, the top label is 9044, which will take the 
packet to R8. The next-next-hop in the path is R4. To provide protection 
for the failure of node R8, R3 would need to send the the packet to R4 
without going through R8. However, the only way R3 can learn that the 
packet needs to go to the R4 is to examine the next label in the stack,
label 9054.  Since R3 knows that R8 has advertised label 9054 as the 
adjacency segment for the link from R8 to R4, R3 knows that a backup path 
can merge back into the original explicit path at R4.   
</t> 
    
</section>

</section>

<section anchor='detailed-soln' 
         title='Detailed Solution using Context Tables'>
<t>This section provides a detailed description of how to 
construct node-protecting backup paths for SR-TE paths using
context tables.  The end result of this description is 
externally visible forwarding behavior 
that can be specified as a packet arriving at a PLR with
a particular incoming label stack and leaving the PLR on a particular 
outgoing interface with a particular outgoing label stack.  
There may be other methods of arriving at the same externally visible 
forwarding behavior as described in draft <xref target ='I-D.bashandy-rtgwg-segment-routing-ti-lfa'/>.  
It is not the intent of this document to
exclude other methods, as long as the externally visible forwarding
behavior is the same as produced by this method.</t> 
	         
<section anchor='context_tables' 
         title='Building Context Tables'>
<t><xref target='RFC5331'/> introduced the concept of
Context Specific Label Spaces and there are various applications making use of this
concept.A context label table on a router represents the Label Forwarding Information 
Base (LFIB) from the point of view of a particular neighbor . Context 
tables are built by constructing incoming label mappings advertised by 
the neighbor and the actions corresponding to those labels. The labels 
advertised by each node are local to the node and may not be unique
across the segment routing domain. The context tables are separate tables 
built on a per-neighbor basis on every node to ensure they represent 
LFIBs of a particular neighbor.</t> 

<t> When a PLR needs to protect an SR-TE path against the failure of a neighbor N, it creates a context table associated with N.
 This context table is populated with the following segment routing forwarding entries:
 <list>
<t>-	All the Prefix-SIDs of the network.
        The programmed incoming label map uses the SRGB of N to compute the input label value. 
        The NHLFE (Next Hop Label Forwarding Entry) is then constructed by looking into all the nexthops for the prefix-SID and
		choosing a loop-free path as explained in <xref target = "sec_context_tables_for_node_sids"/></t>
<t>-	All the Adjacency SIDs advertised by N.
        The NHLFE is constructed as explained in <xref target="sec_context_tables_for_adj_sids"/></t>
</list>

</t>

<t> The following section illustrates how the 
context table is constructed to allow the PLR to provide node-protecting paths for the next-next hops 
in the topology shown in <xref target='example_topology'/> and <xref target='Explicit_path_adj_sid'/>.
</t> 

</section>

<section anchor='sec_context_tables_for_node_sids' 
         title='Node protection for node SIDs'>
   
 <t> <xref target='context_table_node_sid'/> shows the routing table 
entries on R7 corresponding to the node SIDs to reach R1 and R8 for the 
topology in <xref target='example_topology'/>. In the absence of a 
failure, a packet with a label stack whose top label is 1008 will have 
its top label popped by R7 (assuming PHP behavior), and R7 will forward 
the packet to R8. When the interface to R8 is down, the backup next-hop 
entry is used. R7 will pop the top label of 1008, and use the context 
table that R7 computed for R8 to evaluate the next label on the stack. 
</t> 

<figure anchor="context_table_node_sid" title="Building node-protecting backup paths for SR-TE paths involving 
	  node SIDs">
<artwork>    
    R7's Routing Table (partial) 
    Transits routes for Node SIDs for R1 and R8 
   +=============+=============================================+
   | In label    | Outgoing label action                       | 
   +=============+=============================================+
   | 1001        | Primary: pop, fwd to R1                     |
   |             | Backup: pop, lookup context.r1              |
   +-------------+---------------------------------------------+
   | 1008        | Primary: pop, fwd to R8                     | 
   |             | Backup: pop, lookup context.r8              |
   +-------------+---------------------------------------------+

    R7's Context Table for R8 (context.r8, partial)
   +=============+=============================================+
   | In label    | Outgoing label action                       | 
   +=============+=============================================+  
   | 3004        | swap 1004, fwd to R1                        |
   +-------------+---------------------------------------------+
   | 3005        | swap 1005, fwd to R1                        |
   +-------------+---------------------------------------------+
   | 3008        | drop                        |
   +-------------+---------------------------------------------+       
        </artwork>
      </figure>
	  
<t> R7 builds context table for R8 using the following process. R7 
computes the mapping of incoming label to node-sid that R8 expects to 
see based on the SRGB advertised by R8. In the example in <xref 
target='example_topology'/>, R7 can determine that R8 interprets in 
incoming label of 3005 as mapping to the the node SID for R5. </t>

<t> R7 then computes a loop-free backup path to reach R5 which is 
node-protecting with respect to the failure of R8. In this example, the 
backup path computed by R7 to reach R5 without passing through R8 can be 
achieved forwarding the packet to R1 with a top label of 1005, 
corresponding to the node SID for R5 in the context of R1's SRGB. The 
loop-free path computation may be based on a mechanism such as LFA, 
R-LFA, TI-LFA, or constraint based SPF avoiding failure. To populate the 
context table for R8, R7 maps the out label actions corresponding to the 
backup path to R5 to the incoming label 3005. This results in the entry 
for label 3005 showin in context.r8 in <xref 
target='context_table_node_sid'/>. </t>

<t> Therefore, when a packet arrives at R7 with label stack = [1008, 
3005], and the link from R7 to R8 has recently failed, R7 will use 
backup next-hop entry for label 1008 in its main routing table. Based on 
this entry, R7 will pop label 1008, and use context.r8 to lookup the new 
top label = 3005. R7 will swap label 3005 for 1005 and forward the 
packet to R1. This will get the packet to R5 on a node protecting backup 
path.</t> 

<t>Note that R7 activates the node-protecting backup path when it detects 
that the link to R8 has failed. R7 does not know that node R8 has 
actually failed. However, the node-protecting backup path is computed 
assuming that the failure of the link to R8 implies that R8 has failed. 
</t> 

</section>

<section anchor='sec_context_tables_for_adj_sids' 
         title='Node protection for adjacency SIDs'>
		 
 <t> This section gives an example of how to 
constuct node-protecting backup paths when the SR-TE path uses adjacency SIDs.
<xref target ='context_table_adj_sid'/> shows some of the routing table 
entries for R3 corresponding to the sample network shown in <xref target = 
'Explicit_path_adj_sid'/>.   When the top label of the label stack is an
adjacency SID, the PLR needs to recognize that in order to provide 
a node-protecting backup path, it needs to pop the top label and examine
the next label in the context of the next-hop router identified by the 
top label adjacency SID.  In this example, when R3 is constructing its 
routing table, it recognizes that label 9044 corresponds to a next-hop of 
R8, so it installs a backup entry, corresponding to the failure of the link
to R8, when pops label 9044, and then examines the new top label in the
context of R8. </t> 
      
      <figure anchor="context_table_adj_sid" 
	  title="Building node-protecting backup paths for SR-TE paths involving 
	  adjacency SIDs">
        <artwork> 
		
    R3's Routing Table (partial) 
    Transit route for Adj SID 
   +=============+=============================================+
   | In label    | Outgoing label action                       | 
   +=============+=============================================+
   | 9044        | Primary: pop, fwd to R8                     |
   |             | Backup: pop, lookup context.r8              |
   +-------------+---------------------------------------------+


    R3's Context Table for R8 (context.r8, partial)
   +=============+=============================================+
   | In label    | Outgoing label action                       | 
   +=============+=============================================+  
   | 3005        | swap 1005, fwd to R4                        |
   +-------------+---------------------------------------------+	
   | 9054        | pop, fwd to R4                              |
   +-------------+---------------------------------------------+   
        </artwork>
      </figure>
<t> R3 constructs its context table for R8 by determining which labels
R8 expects to receive to accomplish different forwarding actions.  The entry 
for incoming label 3005 in context.r8 in <xref target ='context_table_adj_sid'/> 
corresponds to a node SID.  This entry is computed using the methods described in
  <xref target ='sec_context_tables_for_node_sids'/> </t> 

<t> The entry for incoming label 9054 in context.r8 corresponds to an 
adjacency SID. R3 recognizes that R8 has advertised this adjacency SID 
for the link from R8 to R4 in <xref target = 'Explicit_path_adj_sid'/>. 
So R3 determines the outgoing label action needed to reach R4 without 
passing through R8. This can be accomplished by popping the label 9054, 
and forwarding the packet directly on the link from R3 to R4. 
</t> 
 
 </section>
 
<section anchor='border_node_protection' 
         title='Node protection for edge nodes'>

<t> The node protection mechanism described in the previous sections depends on the assumption 
that the label immediately below the top label in the label stack is understood in the IGP domain.
When the provider edge routers 
exchange service labels via BGP or some other non-IGP mechanism the bottom label is not understood in the IGP domain.
</t> 
 
 
<t> The egress node protection mechanisms described in the draft 
 <xref target ='I-D.ietf-mpls-egress-protection-framework-01'/> 
is applicable to this usecase and no additional changes will be required for SR based networks</t>




    </section>
    </section>
  <section title='Security Considerations' anchor='sec-con'>
    <t>TBD</t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>    </t>

  </section>
  <section title='Acknowledgments'>
    <t>  The authors would like to thank Peter Psenak, Bruno Decreane for their review
	and suggestions. </t>
  </section>
</middle>

<back>
  <references title='Normative References'>
    &RFC5286;
	&RFC5331;   
   
  </references>
  <references title='Informative References'>  
    &RFC2119;
	&RFC8102;
    <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.bashandy-rtgwg-segment-routing-ti-lfa"?>
  </references>
</back>
</rfc>
